Boker tov. Today's official דף daf is יד, Yud Dalet, but we
start in the middle of יג עמוד א Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph
with the new פרק. perek. And you will see by the opening
משנה mishnah and by the גמרא Gemara we're about to read that
I think the גמרא Gemara wanted to give you a break from
all of the sort of heavy discussions and challenging discussions before, we
shift into a very different mode now. So let's take a look
at the first משנה mishnah here. אלו
הן הממונים שהיו במקדש. Elu hen hamemunim shehayu bamikdash. So you know
since we were talking about collecting the שקל shekel and what you
do with the שקל shekel and what you do with the moneys
and how you would set the prices for the suppliers, so it's
we've now be obviously very בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash oriented. So we're
going to now just talk about issues about who has what job
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay so the following people have
are the appointed people, meaning they have some like administrative position in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. יוחנן בן פינחס על החותמות. Yochanan ben
Phinehas al hachotamos. יוחנן בן פינחס Yochanan ben Phinehas oversaw the חותמות.
hachotamos. The חותמות chotamos were the way which we'll see, which we
already alluded to, which was used to buy for people to buy
their נסכים. nesachim. They pay money, they'd get a stamp, they'd go
and take that stamp, that receipt, and then they'd take it to
a supplier and he would supply them with the wine and with
the
whatever. We'll see about it. Anyway, but that's by-the-by because we've been
talking about the נסכים nesachim and you know that came in a
little bit with what you do with the leftover money of the
נסכים nesachim and so on. So יוחנן בן פינחס Yochanan ben Phinehas
oversaw that. אחיה על הנסכים. Achiyah al hanesachim. אחיה Achiyah was oversaw
the נסכים. nesachim. So one is giving the receipt, the other's giving
the guy the נסכים. nesachim. מתיא בן שמואל על הפייסות. Matya ben
Shmuel al hapisos. מתיא בן שמואל Matya ben Shmuel oversaw the פייסות
hapisos which were like lots that they drew to see which כהן
kohein would get which job of some of the more sought-after jobs.
פתחיה על הקינין. Petachia al hakinim. פתחיה Petachia oversaw the bird sacrifices,
you know, and we'll see in the גמרא Gemara why that was
a challenge, but basically also what they would do is, and we
have a whole מסכת קינין Masechet Kinnim because of challenging cases of
when birds get mixed up, but it would also be that people
would bring their own sacrifices and they'd put money in a box
for it, or you know in a and container and then that
money would be taken and used and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
would handle just getting the birds and bringing the bird sacrifices and
doing it all within the same day. So that was obviously a
very challenging thing to oversee.
Now the משנה mishnah makes an interesting sort of shift.
פתחיה זהו מרדכי. Petachia zehu Mordechai. So actually this guy פתחיה Petachia
was
מרדכי. Mordechai. ולמה נקרא שמו פתחיה שהיה פותח דברים ודורשן ויודע בשבעים
לשון. Velama nikra shemo Petachia? Shehaya poseach devarim vedorsham veyodeia beshiv'im lashon.
Because he would open up closed things, he would help, you know,
he would be explicate in things, difficult things, and he would know
the 70 language so like open up, you know, inaccessible languages. So
it's quite fascinating use first of all that it does a little
דרש drash on his name, you know, which sometimes we have the
גמרא Gemara doing by characters in the תורה, Torah, but here you're
doing it about somebody here that actually his name is mentioned in
the משנה, mishnah, and doing this little דרש drash that he's really
the same as this other character and so on. Again, that's something
we're more familiar with with taking two different names somewhere in the
תורה, Torah, like you know the different names of יתרו. Yisro. But
number two also is, if this is מרדכי, Mordechai, then everybody is
so everybody is the we're talking about is from the from the,
you know, first return from the, you know, from the like the
first generation of the בית המקדש השני? Beis Hamikdash Hasheini? I mean
what are we talking about? Which generation are we talking about that
these people served? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara will ask this question.
But I mean what, they all served at the time of מרדכי?
Mordechai? Okay one minute. בן אחיה על חולי מעיים. Ben Achiya al
cholei me'ayim. בן אחיה Ben Achiya oversaw people with digestive problems
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because people would have to eat
a ton of meat and they'd get digestion problems, the כהנים. kohanim.
נחוניא חופר שיחין. Nachunya chofer shichin. נחוניא Nachunya would dig wells, we'll
see what that is. גביני כרוז. Gevini kruz. גביני Gevini was the
announcer. בן גבר, Ben Gever, which is his name, בן גבר על
נעילת שערים, Ben Gever al ne'ilas she'arim, made sure that the gates
were locked at night. כהנים kohanim would do it but he would
oversee them.
It was the לויים, Leviyim, right? That did that?
Yeah yeah yeah, but he would be the head administrator. לויים Leviyim
though, right?
Because לויים Leviyim like... Oh I'm sorry, you're right.
I said כהנים, kohanim, I'm sorry you're right. לויים. Leviyim. The לויים
Leviyim were the שוערים. sho'arim. Thank you. בן בבי ממונה על הפקיע.
Ben Babi memuneh al hapakiya. בן בבי Ben Babi oversaw the פקיע,
pakiya, which we'll see what that is in the גמרא, Gemara, but
I'll tell you now, it's basically the twisting of the wick. בן
ארזא על הצלצל. Ben Arza al hatziltzal. בן ארזא Ben Arza oversaw
the like the chimes which would be the signal for the לויים
Leviyim to begin their singing. הוגרס בן לוי על השיר. Hugras ben
Levi al hashir. הוגרס בן לוי Hugras ben Levi actually oversaw the
choir
itself. בית גרמו על מעשה לחם הפנים. Beis Garmo al ma'aseh lechem
hapanim. We saw them referred to before as well about using the
קטורת ketores to pay בית גרמו Beis Garmo and בית אבטינס. Beis
Avtinas. So here are בית גרמו Beis Garmo and בית אבטינס Beis
Avtinas which we referred to before. בית גרמו Beis Garmo was the
was the was the... house of the כהנים Kohanim that was that
was that did handle the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. This is now
less administrative and they actually, in their household, they held the secrets
of how to make the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim and בית אבטינס Beit Avtinas knew how to
make the קטורת. Ketoret. אלעזר על הפרוכת Elazar al haParochet and פנחס
על המלבוש. Pinchas al haMalbush. We jumped from מרדכי Mordechai to something
which you would have thought was a little bit towards the end
of the בית שני Bayit Sheini and now we're all the way
back to biblical times. So אלעזר, Elazar, assuming it's the אלעזר Elazar
in the תורה, Torah, maybe it's a different אלעזר. Elazar. But again,
the question here is exactly how you get all these figures at
the same time. He oversaw the פרוכת. Parochet. What exactly did that
mean? What did he have to oversee about the פרוכת? Parochet? And
פנחס Pinchas was the one who dressed the כהנים. Kohanim. So כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol presumably. Anyway, maybe this isn't the אלעזר Elazar and
the פנחס Pinchas in the תורה, Torah, but it still raises the
question of which generation we're talking about and if מרדכי, Mordechai, you
know, if everybody really is from the generation of מרדכי. Mordechai. Yes,
Charlie.
Parts of תנ"ך, Tanakh, particularly ספר עזרא Sefer Ezra and נחמיה, Nehemiah,
have unusual amounts of detail about who was doing what. Right.
And
none of this is in תנ"ך. Tanakh.
What can I tell you?
I mean another thing,
מרדכי Mordechai was not a כהן Kohen so a different tribe was
entered.
Look, what I will suggest
is, although I don't know, I haven't checked the academic academic issues
on this, but it's possible that this whole משנה, Mishnah, that there's
a second layer to the משנה, Mishnah, that the statement of פתחיה
הוא מרדכי Petyacha hu Mordechai is a later gloss on the משנה.
Mishnah. And if you take that line out, then we can assume
that everything here is describing one particular generation in time, maybe, you
know, towards the end of the מקדש Mikdash period, which overlapped with
the sort of, you know, beginning of the תנאי Tannaitic period. That
would make a lot more sense. And then assuming that although אלעזר
Elazar and פנחס Pinchas come together, you normally assume it's the biblical,
it's פנחס, Pinchas, you know, it's the biblical one, but okay, maybe
not. Although it is interesting that those are the two also that
do not have a בן ben by their name, don't have a
patronymic or whatever that's called.
But you do kind of wondering because, you know, it seems that
some of these were hereditary, the בית אבטינס, Beit Avtinas, right?
Well, as we'll see, that's because
they held the secret.
Right, right, right, I understand.
But what I find curious is, like, you know, usually, like, the
משנה Mishnah is trying to tell you at least something that would
be some sort of standing הלכה, halacha, or like, you know, dimensions
of the temple, which is, you know, stood for hundreds of years.
Here this is a guy just at one point in time.
Right, I think the naming is less significant, although we'll see what
the גמרא Gemara sort of gives about the naming about an idea
of giving כבוד kavod and honor and so on. But I think
it's more to have us appreciate the different jobs, you know. That's
how I would understand the goal here. But you're right, like why
stop and mention who happened to be at one particular time? Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. רב
חזקיה אמר רבי סימון רבנן. Rav Chizkiyah amar Rabbi Simon Rabbanan. So
a debate of רב חזקיה Rav Chizkiyah and רבנן. Rabbanan. חד אמר
כשירי דור ודור בא למנות. Chad amar kasherei dor vador ba limnot.
It is not at one generation. It's mentioning, like, and this also
addresses Michael's question, it's mentioning of all the generations who are the
ones that really deserve to be singled out because of their, you
know, righteousness or because of how upright that they were. Okay, so
it's the כשר kasher ones from each generation. It shows one particular
one of all the generations to mention and therefore everybody in the
משנה Mishnah could be from all different generations, okay? The ones that
are worth, you know, that are worth mentioning. וחורנא אמר בא למנות
עליהם. Vecharna amar ba limnot aleihem. So that's what it's mentioning. וחורנא
אמר, Vecharna amar, the other one says, מי שהיה באותו דור מנה.
Mi shehaya be'oto dor mana. מצא בדורו Matza bedoro no, whoever was
in that generation, lists the one in his generation, meaning presumably the
author of the משנה Mishnah just listed whoever it was happened to
be in his generation. So now we'll read the parentheses I
guess. מאן דאמר כשירי כל דור ודור בא למנות על כולם הוא
אומר זכר צדיק לברכה. Man de'amar kasherei kol dor vador ba limnot
al kulam hu omer zecher tzadik livracha. Now what does that mean?
It doesn't just mean like the point that the משנה Mishnah is
mentioning people that, you know, are worth mentioning and deserve honor. It
means that there's a משנה Mishnah in יומא Yoma that talks about
different people that did things for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And
it says certain people gave gifts and blah blah blah and other
people, you know, and mentions by the way, for example, the two
here, בית אבטינס Beit Avtinas and what was the other one, בית
גרמו, Beit Garmo, that they didn't teach, they didn't teach
their craft to anyone else. And then it mentions one or two
other people that did bad things. And then it says, על הראשונים
הוא אומר זכר צדיק לברכה. al harishonim hu omer zecher tzadik livracha.
אבל אחרונים הוא אומר שם רשעים ירקב. Aval acharonim hu omer shem
reshaim yirkav. Okay,
that's the משנה Mishnah in יומא. Yoma. So the question is, who
are the ראשונים rishonim and who are the אחרונים? acharonim? So is
this בית גרמו Beit Garmo and בית אבטינס, Beit Avtinas, are they
in the זכר צדיק לברכה zecher tzadik livracha category or in the
שם רשעים ירקב shem reshaim yirkav category? So if you say that
our משנה Mishnah is choosing to mention the ones that were the
כשירי, kasherei, the ones that deserve, you know, recognition, obviously זכר צדיק
לברכה zecher tzadik livracha in that משנה Mishnah in יומא Yoma includes
them. So על כולם הוא אומר זכר צדיק לברכה. al kulam hu
omer zecher tzadik livracha. מאן דאמר מי שהיה באותו דור מנה מצא
בדורו Man de'amar mi shehaya be'oto dor mana matza bedoro no,
that they were only mentioning who happened to be in the generation.
that generation that the משנה Mishna was mentioned. It doesn't indicate that
anybody was particularly good or important. So then, על כולם הוא אומר
שם רשעים ירקב. al kulam hu omer shem reshaim yirkav. So שם
רשעים ירקב shem reshaim yirkav would include בית גרמו Beit Garmo and
בית אבטינס. Beit Abtinas. And we're going to see this repeated, this
whole question about were these guys good guys or bad guys. On
the one hand they were good that they preserved the skills and
they did a good job. On the other hand they refused to
share it with anyone else. So it depends whether you read that
the משנה Mishna is singling those people, these people out for recognition
or not. Now מי נאמר זכר צדיק לברכה. mi ne'emar Zecher Tzadik
Livracha. So if you say שם רשעים ירקב shem reshaim yirkav applies
to these guys, בית גרמו Beit Garmo and בית אבטינס, Beit Abtinas,
so who does the זכר צדיק לברכה Zecher Tzadik Livracha go on
in that משנה יומא? Mishna Yoma? Again, this is all referring to
a משנה יומא Mishna Yoma which you're supposedly to have known. So
על בן קטין וחבריו, al Ben Katin v'chaverav, only on בן קטין
Ben Katin and the other people that were mentioned at the beginning
of that משנה. Mishna. Okay, so are בית גרמו Beit Garmo and
בית אבטינס Beit Abtinas good guys? Are they זכר צדיק לברכה? Zecher
Tzadik Livracha? Are they שם רשעים ירקב? shem reshaim yirkav? So it
depends who you ask, like a lot of things. Okay, a good
guy or a bad guy.
Why specifically בית גרמו Beit Garmo and בית אבטינס? Beit Abtinas?
Because they are mentioned in the משנה יומא. Mishna Yoma. And in
the משנה יומא Mishna Yoma it first starts with people that are
obviously great guys, and great women actually, has הילני Hilni I think
and so on. Then it has on the bottom somebody who obviously
did wrong things. And then in the middle it had בית אבטינס
Beit Abtinas and בית גרמו Beit Garmo and it mentions that they
didn't share their knowledge. So you're inclined to read it in the
שם רשעים ירקב shem reshaim yirkav category, but maybe not. Okay and
that's what the question is.
But didn't they have an answer?
We're getting to it. We'll see it later. אמר רב יונה, Amar
Rav Yona, כתיב, ketiv, okay the פסוק pasuk says לכן אחלק לו
ברבים ואת עצומים יחלק שלל, lachen achalek lo barabim v'et atzumim yachalek
shalal, I will divide for him amongst the masses and with the
mighty ones he will you know divide the booty. זה רבי עקיבא
zeh Rabbi Akiva שהתקין מדרש הלכות ואגדות. she'hitkin midrash halachot v'agadot.
So this idea of עצומים atzumim is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
established the הלכות halachot and the הגדות. agadot. Now exactly what that
means he established is not clear and how it's you know, it's
what do you call it, how it's fitting it into into this
פסוק, pasuk, but it might mean as the בבלי Bavli sometimes says
that he took a lot that was before him and disorganized and
he sort of gathered it up and reorganized it into categories. So
it might be focusing on the word יחלק yachalek to divide up
the wealth that preceded him and dividing it up into you know,
into
conceptual categories.
I mean הגדות? agadot?
I assume he means אגדה? agadda? הגדותיו? aggadotov? Yeah הגדותיו.
aggadotov.
But
exactly, and תוספות Tosfos says הלכה והמדרש הלכה. halacha v'hamidrash halacha. Oh
so
that's interesting. אגדה agadda meaning like מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha. Right.
That's
interesting as usually
we don't describe, right,
normally what they say to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is עקיבא כלך
לך אצל נגעים ואהלות. Akiva kelach lecha etzel nega'im v'ohelot. What does
it have to do with אגדה? agadda? Right, so all right. So
it could be, it's interesting, have to see if there are parallels
to the use of the word אגדה agadda for מדרש תנאים. Midrash
Tanna'im. Okay. ויש אומרים אלו אנשי כנסת הגדולה. v'yesh omrim elu anshei
knesset hagedola. These are the people of אנשי כנסת הגדולה. anshei knesset
hagedola. Now we're going to see what that means. תיקנו. tiknu. What
did they establish? אלא מה תיקן? ela ma tiken? So what did
he establish? They or רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
No it says מה תיקן, ma tiken, is that the singular?
Yeah
I know but I don't think so. I think we're still on
the אנשי כנסת הגדולה. anshei knesset hagedola. אלא מה תיקן, זה כללות
ופרטות. ela ma tiken zeh klalot u'pratot. So it's כלל klal and
פרט. prat. What does that mean? So let's take a look. אמר
רבי אבהו, כתיב, Amar Rabbi Abahu Ketiv hold on let me just
see what it says. Oh actually no,
oh okay. Oh I see I see. The side says, the side
divides the פסוק pasuk two ways. אחלק לו ברבים achalek lo barabim
again switches, maybe assumes that this is implied or reads it in.
אחלק לו ברבים achalek lo barabim is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And
then
ואת עצומים יחלק שלל v'et atzumim yachalek shalal is אלו
אנשי כנסת הגדולה.
elu
anshei knesset hagedola. תיקנו. tiknu. So yes, what were
you saying? עצומים? Atzumim? No, דוב Dov was saying. אלא מה תיקן
זה, ela ma tiken zeh, meaning רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. That's what
מיכה Micah was
saying.
Okay. All right
I see. אלא מה תיקן ela ma tiken, זה כללות ופרטות. zeh
klalot u'pratot. What did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva מתקן? metaken? The כלל
klal and
the
פרט. prat. Thank you. Okay, I was misreading that. All right. So
exactly what this is כלל ופרט klal u'prat as opposed to הלכות
ואגדות. halachot v'agadot. I mean כלל ופרט klal u'prat maybe again is
this point more about organizing the material. הלכות ואגדות, halachot v'agadot, you
know,
maybe it's you know what exactly that's referring
to, what he was the first to clearly articulate the הלכות ואגדות,
halachot v'agadot, that's certainly not true by רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So
not exactly clear what exactly is being sort of debated about who
did the הלכות ואגדות. Halachot ve-Aggadot. אמר רבי אבהו amar Rabbi Abbahu,
כתיב ketiv, משפחת סופרים יושבי יעבץ. Mishpachat Sofrim Yoshvei Yabetz. The family
of the סופרים Sofrim who dwell in יעבץ, Yabetz, whatever that means,
it might be a place. Anyway, מה תלמוד לומר סופרים? Mah Talmud
lomar Sofrim? What does it mean סופרים? Sofrim? And this is a
famous מדרש. Midrash. Why were the early generations of the rabbis called
סופרים? Sofrim? אלא שעשו את התורה ספורות ספורות. Ela she-asu et ha-Torah
sfurot sfurot. They made the Torah into numbers. What does this mean?
So again this goes into the organizing activity of חזל, Chazal, of
the sort of traditions, but the way in which they sort of
helped organize and categorize things and make mnemonics with them. So for
example, now we're going to list a lot of משניות Mishnayot that
use numbers. חמשה לא יתרמו תרומה, Chamisha lo yitremu Trumah, five people
can't take תרומה. Trumah. ה דברים חייבים בחלה. Hey devarim chayavim be-Challah.
חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות צרותיהן, Chamesh Esreh Nashim potrot tzaroteihen, fifteen women
exempt their co-wives from יבום. Yibbum. שלשים וששה כריתות בתורה, Shloshim ve-Shesha
Kretot ba-Torah, there are thirty-six, these are all beginnings of משניות. Mishnayot.
Okay, thirty-six כריתות Kretot in the Torah. שלשה עשר דבר נאמרו בנבילת
העוף הטהורה, Shlosha-Asar davar neemru be-neveilat ha-of ha-tehorah, thirteen things are said
by a carcass of a kosher bird. ארבע אבות נזיקין, Arba Avot
Nezikin, four main categories of damages of animals. אבות
מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת, Avot Melachot Arba'im chaseir achat, the מלאכות Melachot
on שבת Shabbat are forty minus one. So all of that was
done by the early generations. So it's fascinating here. By the way,
I knew a guy that had this whole little thing about אחד
מי יודע Echad Mi Yodea all the way to שלשה עשר מי
יודע Shlosha-Asar Mi Yodea to link it up to a משנה Mishnah
that had those numbers. שנים Shnayim this, שלשה Shlosha that, anyway. ארבע
אבות נזיקין, Arba Avot Nezikin, חמשה לא יתרמו, Chamisha lo yitremu, ששה,
Shisha, anyway.
Pretty genius. Anyway, so you can think that could be an assignment
for over the weekend to try to come up with that. Anyway,
the point here what's fascinating about this גמרא Gemara is that it
recognizes the process of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be-al Peh, not necessarily
in the issue of like development of הלכה Halacha that might have
הלכה Halacha might, you know, evolve over time, but in the sense
of more the organization of the material. Meaning when it speaks about
הלכות ואגדות Halachot ve-Aggadot established by אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedolah,
meaning that's like suggestive. What does it mean they established the הלכות?
Halachot? You know, again, maybe they took practices that were established and
then they articulated those practices as laws, right? Maybe they looked around
them, saw what people were doing and then sort of articulated it
as הלכה. Halacha. Exactly what it means to establish הלכות Halachot is
interesting and but then we're talking about the sort of organizing efforts
that were done with those traditions. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva organized
things thematically. There was a literary way of giving numbers to things,
ways of bringing the material together and making it coherent, making it
able to be remembered and that was an early activity in the
sort of process here by the early rabbis. So אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rabbi Elazar, כתיב, Ketiv, the פסוק Pasuk says, so anyway what
does that, that was all fascinating, but what does that have to
do with us? So it might be the link over here. So
let's take a look, the connection we're about to make. לעזרא הכהן
הסופר, Le-Ezra ha-Kohen ha-Sofer, Ezra the Cohen the סופר. Sofer. So we
just mentioned the סופרים Sofrim of the rabbis, here we have a
כהן Kohen who's a סופר. Sofer. So מה תלמוד לומר סופר? Mah
Talmud lomar Sofer? What does it mean he's a סופר? Sofer? אלא
כשם שהיה סופר בדברי תורה כך היה סופר בדברי חכמים. Ela keshem
she-hayah Sofer be-divrei Torah kach hayah Sofer be-divrei Chachamim. The same way
there was a counting in the words of the Torah, meaning that
they attribute to עזרא, Ezra, meaning it really should be the other
way: כשם שהיה סופר בדברי חכמים כך היה סופר בדברי תורה. Keshem
she-hayah Sofer be-divrei Chachamim kach hayah Sofer be-divrei Torah. Meaning the same
way we just mentioned before that the rabbis created numbers as a
way of organizing their material and sort of passing it out, so
עזרא Ezra numbered the Torah. And this is attributing to עזרא Ezra
the work that we know of the early Masoretes, which is to
say, you know, exactly how many פסוקים, Psukim, how many times is
it written היא, Hi, how many times is it written הוא, Hu,
how many times is it spelled מלא, Maleh, how many times is
it spelled חסר, Chaser, what's half the Torah in words, what's half
the Torah in letters. All of those things are ways in ensuring
the accuracy of the text. So we are assuming that that's what
חזל Chazal did with the rabbinic material, the Tannaitic material, to preserve
its memory and its accuracy, and that's what עזרא Ezra did with
the written text of the Torah.
Yes, maybe this is so obvious but I think it's very revealing
that the word ספר Sefer and the word סופר.
Sofer.
In other words, everything that we mean by a ספר Sefer has
embedded in its definition and identity a sense of structure and organization.
Interesting, meaning לספר Lesaper to tell over but it's also לספור Lispor
to count.
And to count that there's a structure, that there's a number of
words, there are sections, there are פסוקים. Psukim.
Right, right. It's a good point. I mean the simplest sense of
סופר Sofer obviously is from לספר Lesaper which means to tell and
it's a book that tells a story, but the idea here that
סופר Sofer also means as you said, you know, very much counted
and numbered. ספר, Sefer, right.
Okay. רבי חגי בשם רבי שמואל בר נחמן. Rabbi Chagai be-shem Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachman. הראשונים, Harishonim, this is such a great line, הראשונים,
Harishonim, the early ones, the early תנאים, Tannaim, חרשו, charshu, they plowed,
וזרעו, v'zar'u, they planted, ניכשו, nichshu, they weeded, כסחו, kisschu, עדרו, idru,
קצרו, katzru, עמרו, amru, they did all these various things, they hoed,
they harvested, they put it into piles, the wheat, דשו, dashu, זרו,
zaru, they threshed, they
winnowed, בררו, berru, טחנו, tachnu, they took out the, you know, the
פסולת, psollet, the, you know, the stones, they ground it into wheat,
הרקידו, hirkidu, לשו, lashu, they sifted, they kneaded, קטפו ואפו, kitfu v'afu,
it's like, you know, they patted it down, the dough, they baked
the dough, they did everything to make the Torah accessible to us.
ואנו אין לנו מה לאכול. v'anu ein lanu mah le'echol. And we
don't have anything to eat. They did everything, we have it so
easy, and we still have a hard time to access the Torah.
Such a beautiful idea of appreciating how much, like we just come
and we read the משנה. Mishna. Well, what came before the משנה?
Mishna? What did you have to do to what was around before
in order to get to the stage that you could articulate it
in this organized fashion in the משנה? Mishna?
We just come into דף יומי Daf Yomi every day, right, exactly.
But no, but this is, it's not just, but the point really
is how much to appreciate, look, you know, it's the same thing
you could say in a very literal terms, you go to the
supermarket, you buy a loaf of bread, you ever take a moment
to appreciate, you know, how many people were involved and how much
effort was involved in the getting it to the table? I mean,
just look at the list of the מלאכות melachot that that requires,
right? So the same is true when you come and you open
up a גמרא Gemara and even you read a משנה Mishna and
they're looking at all the earlier material. What existed before the משנה?
Mishna? How much did you have to do to transform whatever sort
of oral traditions and practices that there was into articulated law, like
you were saying before about הלכות, halachot, into organized, into getting it
all to this stage? And look, and we still have a tough
time. רבי אבא בר זמינא בשם רבי זעירא, Rabbi Abba bar Zamina
beshem Rabbi Ze'eira, אם הוון קדמאין מלאכין, in havon kadma'in malachin, so
now that's the next, the next thing, which is also paralleled in
the בבלי, Bavli, if the earlier ones were מלאכים malachim or angels,
אנן בני אנש, anan benei enash, then we're just people. ואין הוון
בני אנש, v'in havon benei enash, if they were people, אנן חמורין,
anan chamorin, then we're donkeys. אמר רבי מנא בההיא שעתא אמרית, amar
Rabbi Mana b'hahi sha'ata amrit, at that time I said, or it
was said, אפילו כחמוריה דרבי פנחס בן יאיר לא דמינן, afilu k'chamorei
d'Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair lo daminan, even like the donkey of Rabbi
Pinchas ben Yair we're not comparable. So we're not even, we're not
even a good donkey, we're just a normal donkey. Now we get
to tell the story about the donkey of Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair,
again, this is exactly paralleled in the בבלי, Bavli, not exactly, but
it's paralleled. חמורתיה דרבי פנחס בן יאיר, chamortei d'Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair,
so the donkey of Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair, גנבוה ליסטים בליליא, ganvuha
listim b'leilya,
bandits stole him in the middle of the night. עבדת טמירה גבון
תלתא יומין, avdat temira gavon tlata yomin, so they hid him by
themselves for three days, they, you know, they had the donkey with
them hiding in hiding for three days. ולא טעמה כלום, v'lo ta'ama
klum, and he refused to eat. Okay, he went on a hunger
strike. בתר תלתא יומין, v'tar tlata yomin, after three days, אמרו למחזרא,
amru l'machzara, they changed their mind and they decided to return it.
They didn't want to have to deal with a dead donkey on
their hands and then they'd have to explain it and they'd get
into trouble and they'd be found out. אמרי, amrei,
אפקינהו מן הכא, apkinei min hacha, let's get him out of here,
דלא תימות גבן, d'lo temut gaban, so he shouldn't die on us.
אפיקוה, afikuha, so they got rid of, they chased him away. אפיקוה,
afikuha, אזלת וקמת לה על תרעא דמריה, azlat v'kamat lah al tar'a
d'mareh, so he went and he stood by the door of his
master, he knew he was a homing donkey, he knew how to
get home. שרית מגהקא, sharyat megaheka, he began to, you know, to
moan or whatever sound, what sound does a donkey make? Neigh? Bray,
right? Bray, he began to bray. אמר לון, amar lon, so Rabbi
Pinchas ben Yair said to them, his students or whoever was there,
פתחון להדא עלובתא, pitchun l'hada aluvta, open up the door for this,
you know,
forsaken one, thank you. דאית לה תלתא יומין דלא טעמה כלום, d'it
lah tlata yomin d'lo ta'ama klum, it's gone three days without eating
anything. He knew that his donkey wouldn't eat when it, you know,
when it wasn't at the house. Now, maybe it was because, as
I said, a hunger strike, but we'll see another reason why it
wouldn't
eat. פסקן לה, paskan leh, so they opened up the, they opened
up the door for the donkey, ועלת לה, v'alat lah, and they
brought it in. אמר לון, amar lon, he said to them, I
wonder, into the house, into the barn, anyway, אמר לון, amar lon,
he said to them, יהבון לה כלום תאכל, yehavun lah klum te'echal,
so give him something to eat. יהבון קמה שעורין, yehavun kamah se'orin,
they gave him barley, ולא בעת למיכל, v'lo ba'at l'meichal, and he
didn't want to eat it, he didn't want to eat it. אמרין
ליה, amrin leh, they said to him, רבי לא בעת למיכל, Rebbi
lo ba'at l'meichal, he doesn't want to eat the barley. אמר לון,
amar lon, he said to them, מתקנין אינון, metaknin inun, have you
fixed it? So meaning have you, have you fixed it in the
physical sense, have you, like, removed the, you know, the, the פסולת,
psollet, like the, you know, the stones and the chaff from it?
אמרין ליה אין, amrin leh in, yes, we did. אמר לון, amar
lon, so he said to them, והרמתון דמאי, v'harimtun demai, have you
taken away, off דמאי? demai? Not even definite תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot.
It was brought, it was bought from עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, so
it only had an obligation of דמאי, demai, of a rabbinic need
of taking תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot.
And you didn't do that?
Well, we're only feeding it to the donkey and you're allowed to
feed your animals דמאי. demai. So they said great, it's an animal,
we can feed our animals דמאי. demai. Ah, maybe other animals, yes,
but... No, we didn't! Why why why take דמאי? Demai? You know,
it's only דמאי Demai you can feed it to animals. So,
לא, Lo, כן, Kein, אלפון רבי, Alfun Rebbi, רבי Rebbi taught us:
הלוקח זרע לבהמה, Halokeiach zera lebeheimah, if you say halokeiach if you
take דמאי Demai for planting or לבהמה lebeheimah or for feeding your
animals or
קמח לעורות kemach le'oros or to use flour for the for leather
so you're not taking it for eating then שמן לאור shemen la'or
or oil for a for a lamp פטור מן הדמאי patur min
hademai you don't have to separate off דמאי Demai I mean תרומת
מעשר terumas ma'aser from the דמאי. Demai. So what we did, אמר
להן, amar lehen, he said to them, מאי נעביד לה להא עלובתה,
mai na'avid lah leha aluvta, what should we do to this forsaken
one? דאי מחמרא אגרמא de'ee machmera agarmah because it is it's מחמיר
machmir on itself על עצמה. al atzmah. By the way, notice that
word Dov, you enjoy the language right? עצמה, atzmah,
עצמך, atzmecha,
yourself is עצם etzem is bone right? And גרמא garma in Aramaic
too, גרמא garma is a bone and גרמא garma is is yourself.
Well also חמור chamor and he's מחמיר. machmir.
Yeah that was cool, that was nice, I hadn't thought about that
point. חמור chamor is מחמיר. machmir. But I'm just pointing out generally
the word of גרמא garma means yourself and it means a bone
both in Hebrew and Aramaic. Anyway that's a good point, a חמור
chamor is מחמיר. machmir. So חמור chamor it's מחמיר machmir on itself,
סגן ורמו דמיא, sagan u'ramu demaya,
so go you know it's enough meaning you should go ahead and
take the דמאי. Demai. סגן ורמו דמיא, sagan u'ramu demaya, I mean
sorry excuse me, sagin like they went, סגן ורמו דמיא, sagan u'ramu
demaya, they went and they took the דמאי Demai ואכלה ve'achala and
then it finally ate. Which probably explains why it didn't eat when
it was handed the bandit's because they were feeding it I'm sure
טבל, tevel, גזל, gezel, so you see how righteous the חמור chamor
was. If the people of the previous generations were people we're not
even at the level of the חמור chamor of פנחס בן יאיר.
Pinchas ben Yair. The thing about the donkey being מחמיר machmir on
itself, now I just have to tell you this joke which is
that I think this is told in the name of the נודע
ביהודה, Noda BiYehuda, that there was this שוחט shochet from the neighboring
town that every week would come over and ask him שאלות sheilos
about טרפות treifos of the animals he slaughtered that week. But then
a few weeks went by and he didn't come so finally he
started coming back so he said to him, he said, I don't
understand, where were you over these last few weeks? He said, look,
I would come because I have to come because I don't want
to be you know selling טרפות treifos but it's a big שוואפ,
shvapp, it's half a day here, it's half a day back then
one שבת Shabbos I was hearing as they were reading in the
שול, shul, they were reading the the פרשה parsha and they said
ובשר בשדה טרפה לא תאכלו לכלב תשליכון אותו. u'vasar basadeh tereifah lo
socheilu lakelev tashlichun oso. So I said oh, I've got I've got
a solution! Let me take some meat from an animal I have
a ספק, safek, I'll throw it to the dog. If he eats
it it's a טרפה, treifah, if he doesn't eat it it's not
a טרפה. treifah. So the נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda says, hm, he
said, that's that's very interesting. He said, so so why'd you come
back? He says the dog was too big of
a מחמיר!
machmir! Yeah exactly exactly. Anyway we just read the other day a
week or two ago about the עקדה, Akeida, שבו פה עם החמור
shevu po im hachamor and עם הדומה
לחמור,
am
hadomeh lachamor, yeah you know which is quote unquote the non-Jewish people.
But here we're saying we're not even at that level. It was
interesting so you know as opposed to like you know that sort
of narrowing looking at it here we're saying you know what it's
anybody who like you know doesn't keep to the...
Yeah, but this is in a sort of self-deprecating way in talking
about the greatness of the previous generations. By the way, that מדרש
midrash is talking specifically about about עבדים avadim I believe. Anyway, so
let's keep on going so that was a nice little thing which
presumably was the idea of
you know, it's not exactly clear to me how it ties how
it ties in I gotta tell you.
I'm not exactly sure how this how this whole idea of the
greatness of the previous generations is. The one thing is עזרא הכהן
הסופר, Ezra HaKohen HaSofer, but even that did not exactly tie in
to the rest of the משנה mishnah and the theme about what's
going on in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So anyway okay פתחיה
על הקינים, Pesachiah al hakinim, we skip over some of the people
mentioned in the משנה mishnah and we talk about פתחיה Pesachiah who
we heard was מרדכי Mordechai oversees the bird sacrifices. So בוא וראה
מה גדול הוא כוחו של אותו איש, bo u'rei mah gadol hu
kocho shel oso ish, פותח דברים ודורשן. poteiach devarim vedorshan. Okay, come
and see how great he was, he could open up things and
explicate them. All right, יודע בשבעים לשון yodeia beshivim lashon
and he knew seventy languages. תני, tani, סנהדרין שיש בו שנים שיכולים
לדבר וכולם ראויים לשמוע. Sanhedrin sheyesh bo shnayim sheyecholim ledaber vekhulam reuyim
lishmoa.
If you have a סנהדרין Sanhedrin of seventy, two of them can
speak all languages and the rest of them can understand other languages
הרי זו ראויה לסנהדרין, harei zu reuyah le-Sanhedrin,
that's the minimum requirements
for
a סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. ג' הרי זו בינונית, Gimmel harei zu beinonis,
if three people can speak all seventy languages that's an average סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. Everybody else needs to understand. ד' הרי זו חכמה, Daled harei
zu chakhmah,
that's a wise סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. וביבנה היו בו ד', u'veYavneh hayu vo
daled, and there were four in the סנהדרין Sanhedrin of יבנה. Yavneh.
בן עזאי Ben Azzai ובן זומא u'ven Zoma ובן חכינאי u'ven Chakhinai
ורבי אלעזר בן מתיא. veRebbi Elazar ben Masya.
Okay, so these were the four that could speak all שבעים לשון.
shivim lashon. אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, פעם אחת יבשה ארץ
ישראל, pa'am achas yavsha Eretz Yisrael,
one time there was a very dry a drought in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael ולא ידעו מהיכן להביא עומר, velo yadu meiheichan lehavi omer,
they didn't know where to bring the עומר omer from והוה תמן
חד אילם vehavah saman chad ileim and there was one person who
was mute. דהוה יהיב חדא ידיה על גגות, de-havah yahiv chada yadeih
al gagot, he put one hand on a rooftop, וחדא ידיה על
צריפים, ve-chada yadeih al tzrifim, and one on the top of like
a teepee. אייתוהו קמיה דפתחיה, Aituhu kamei de-Pethachyah,
they brought him in front of פתחיה. Pethachyah. Remember פתחיה Pethachyah could
figure out hidden things, so he's going to interpret this mime. So
they brought him in front of פתחיה. Pethachyah. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
and he said to the people, אית אתר דמתקרי גגות צריפים או
צריפים גגות? it atar de-mitkari gagot tzrifim o tzrifim gagot?
Is there a place in Israel called גגות צריפים gagot tzrifim or
צריפים גגות? tzrifim gagot? אזלו להתם, azalu le-hatam, so they went there
presumably, one of presumably גגות צריפים, gagot tzrifim, I don't know, ואשכחו,
ve-ashkechu, and they found that they had that that place had grain
that they could use for the עומר. omer. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
בון, Amar Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Bun, פעם אחת, pa'am achat, another similar
story, there was one time נשתדף כל העולם כולו, nishtadef kol ha-olam
kulo, there was like a blight, thank
you, on the entire world.
I mean the entire world, not just Israel. ולא היו יודעין מהיכן
להביא עומר, ve-lo hayu yode'in meiheichan lehavi omer, they didn't know where
to bring the עומר omer from. והוה תמן חד אילם, va-havah taman
chad illem, there was a mute person דהוה יהיב ידיה על עיניו,
de-havah yahiv yadeih al einav, one hand on his eyes, וידיה על
סוכרא דסוחר, ve-yadeih al sukhra de-sokher, and one hand on like the
opening of a well. אייתוהו לקמיה דפתחיה, Aituhu lekamei de-Pethachyah, they brought
him in front of פתחיה. Pethachyah. אמר להו, Amar lehu, and he
said to them, אית אתר דמתקרי עין סוכר או סוכר עין? it
atar de-mitkari ein sokher o sokher ein? Is there a place called
עין סוכר ein sokher or סוכר עין? sokher ein? Presumably עין סוכר
ein sokher is the place. ואזלו לתמן, ve-azalu letaman, they went there,
ואשכחו, ve-ashkechu, and they found and they found the wheat that they
could use. Now, ג' נשים הביאו קיניהן, Gimel nashim heviu kineihan,
three women brought their קינים kinim right to פתחיה Pethachyah because again
פתחיה Pethachyah is Mordechai, he's so brilliant, and קינים kinim he oversaw
the קינים, kinim, and now we're going to see. Now again, if
you read the simple sense is why you need somebody like Mordechai
according to this understanding anyway over the קינים kinim is because the
whole we have a whole מסכת masechet on it and when they
get mixed up it creates all of these problems. But the גמרא
Gemara is going to give another story with קינים kinim that's more
similar to the previous one. Okay, so three women came to him.
אחת אומרת, achat omeret,
one said לעינתי, le-einati, this is for my עינתי. einati. Now עינתי
einati can mean like eye, but it can also mean עינתי einati
as a like עין ayin as we just said עין סוכר ein
sokher or a well. So we're going to see how he interprets
it. ואחת אומרת לימתי, ve-achat omeret le-yamati, this is for my ocean.
ואחת אומרת לזיבתי, ve-achat omeret le-zivati, this is for my presumably flow.
So זו שאומרת לעינתי, zu she-omeret le-einati, the one that said my
eye, סברין למימר, savrin lemeimar, we thought it meant שופעת כמעיין, shofat
ke-ma'ayan, that I have, you know, had a flow and I'm and
I've been like, you know, like the like the flow of a
well of a wellspring and therefore I'm bringing it because I'm a
זבה. zavah. Now נדה niddah doesn't bring a קרבן, korban, but a
זבה zavah does. So and a זבה zavah by the way is
a woman who bleeds not during her menstrual period. So if she's
flowing like a like a like a well, you know, like a
spring, then then then it means I bled not during my menstrual
period and it's for the fact that I'm a זבה. zavah.
That's what we thought she meant, which is a certainly reasonable interpretation.
Where was I? Okay. אמר להו, Amar lehu, no, so פתחיה Pethachyah
said to us, בעיינה סכנתא, be-aynah sakanta, no,
it meant that I had some type of a of a of
an injury, I was in danger in my eye, and I my
life was at risk, and I'm bringing this just as like as
a thanksgiving, it's a total עולה, olah, it's not a קרבן korban
for a זבה, zavah, and there's a difference, one is עולה, olah,
the other is חטאת ועולה. chatat ve-olah. So therefore he said no
no no that's not what she means, she means it's a נדבה.
nedavah. I have no idea. Maybe he said and he walked out
and left because remember also by the way they put their money
into
the into the box and then they they use the funds afterwards.
So you have to know why people are putting the money in
the box, okay? Okay, so זו שאומרת, zu she-omeret, so okay. וזו
שאומרת לימתי, ve-zu she-omeret le-yamati, the one that said my ocean, סברין
למימר, savrin lemeimar, שופעת כים, shofat ke-yam,
I'm, you know, flowing like an ocean, so again I have a
flow that goes beyond my menstrual period and I'm a זבה. zavah.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, no he said to her, בימא סכנתא, be-yama
sakanta, no
it means that I was I was endangered in the ocean, I
almost lost my life and again it's a נדבה. nedavah. זו שאומרת
לזיבתי, zu she-omeret le-zivati, now this seems pretty clear, the one that
said for my flow, סברין למימר, savrin lemeimar, זבה ממש, zavah mamash,
she's a זבה. zavah. אמר להו Amar lehu he said to us,
זאב בא ליטול את בנה, ze'ev ba litol et benah, no it
means that a a wolf came to try to take away her
child and she got saved and again it's a נדבה. nedavah. Now
again, how the heck did he know this? So presumably one imagines
that there was something about the body language he was reading, the
context he was reading, and this is why he's so brilliant. Just
on paper, there are other explanation makes more sense, but he was
able to pick up something about the demeanor of the person that
he was able to interpret it in this way.
Yes, the תלמוד Talmud knows obviously, the תלמוד's Talmud assumption, right, that
נדה niddah was a natural cycle and the זבה zavah was unnatural,
right. Right, yeah, sure. Yeah,
sure.
Okay. Yeah?
So this is not an
ordinary תודה todah offering?
Not an ordinary, no it's an עולה, olah, it's an עולה olah
like yeah not a תודה. todah.
She she's bringing an עולה olah
as as a type of thanksgiving, correct. Okay. בן אחיה, Ben Achyah,
now בן אחיה Ben Achyah was the one who oversaw some. ailment,
stomach problems, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
very practically, על ידי שהיו הכהנים Kohanim, הולכים יחיפים על הרצפה *al
yedei shehayu hakohanim
holchim yecheifim al
haritzpah*, the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* would go barefoot on the floor and
they would stuff themselves with meat, they'd have to eat all those
קרבנות *Korbanot* that were brought in there, all the חטאת *Chatat* and
אשם *Asham*. Okay, and they would drink water because they weren't allowed
any other thing apparently in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*
other than water for some reason. So, היו באים לידי חולי מעיים
*hayu baim lidei choli me'ayim*, that led to stomach ailments. So, it's
quite fascinating that it assumes that if you're drinking water, it's part
of the problem. One minute. והוה ידע *Vahavei yeda*, and he would
know, האי דיין חמר טב למעיא *hai dein chamar tav lime'aya*, what's
good wine? The problem if you've got a stomach issues is drinking
the right wine. That's the solution. So, he would know what would
be the right wine for stomach problems. והאי דיין חמר טב למעיא
*vehai dein chamar tav lime'aya*
would be good for the stomach, meaning presumably to help you help
you what do
you call it
go to the bathroom. What's that called when you take something for
a laxative? That would be oh no so no the opposite. Presumably
טב למעיא *tav lime'aya* might it would help
it would help you keep it in. והאי דיין חמר סמם למעיא
*vehai dein chamar samam lime'aya* and which one would be a laxative
for the stomach and help you help you get it out. So,
anyway, he knew which wines to feed them, which one would be
a laxative and which one would be a what's the other one
called? Pepto what's the other one called, the opposite of a laxative,
a constipative? I don't know. Anyway, okay, so he would know which
wines to feed them. All right, so now let's go on. Yes,
please.
I think this story is also things to show people who could
not communicate with the people in charge of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*,
like בן אחיה *Ben Achyah* who had to do pantomime, the women
who said one thing when they meant another, so they needed someone
who could interpret and who could be the bridge.
Oh, that's a nice point.
So, there was this gap
between the
people in
authority and the ability for them to really understand, right,
and the greatness of that one guy בן
אחיה *Ben Achyah*, right, who could bridge
the gap, right, who could speak their language, right.
Very nicely said. Okay. נחוניא חופר שיחין *Nechunya Chofir Shichin*, Nechunya would
dig wells. שהיה חופר שיחין ומערות *Shehayah chofer shichin ume'arot*, he would
dig wells and, you know, מערות *me'arot* are like caves, other types
of
things that you would dig in order to get access to water.
והוה ידע *Vahavei yeda*, and he would know, האי דיין כיף מקורר
*hai dein keif mekorar*, which type of a rock if you dig
into it or, you know, you can get out cold water from
it. There'll be like cold water underground.
Yes, because they would need it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash.
*Beis HaMikdash*, yeah, בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* related, yes. והאי
דיין כיף אית ביה שרברבי *Vehai dein keif it beih sharvrari*... let's
try that again. שרברורי *Sharvruri*. I can't do it.
שרברב
*Shravrav* is a plumber. Thank you.
שרברב *Shravrav*, I can't even pronounce it. Okay. שרברורי *Sharvruri*, okay, there
you go. שרברורי *Sharvruri*. Engineer. No, no, but anyway, the way they
say it means is it means, like שרב *sherav* is heat. So,
שרברורי
*sharvruri* would mean hot water. ועד היכן שרברביה מטא *Ve'ad heichan sharvruryei
mati*, and how far it would go down into the earth, the
stream of hot water. Okay. אמר amar, רבי Rebbi, אליעזר *Amar Rabbi
Eliezer*, ומת בנו בצמא *umet bno btzama*. Now, here is a challenging
theological
episode that happened, the whole question of theodicy. Here's this amazing guy
that he makes sure that the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* always had
water, always had the exact right water that it needed, and his
son died in thirst. Died because he didn't have water. So, now
the גמרא *Gemara* gets into a fascinating reflection on how to make
sense of that phenomenon. So, let's take a look. So, אמר רבי
חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chanina*, מאן דאמר רחמנא וותרן *man de'amar Rachmana vatran*,
ייוותרון בני מעוהי *yivaterun bnei me'ohi*. So, this is a famous line.
Whoever says God is a וותרן *vatran*, God like just lets things
go, he forgives, like you don't have to do תשובה *teshuvah*, you
know, yeah you sin it's not a big deal don't worry about
it. If you think that's the way God acts, then your stomach
should be let go as well. So, which just like means that
you can never you know God there's מידת הדין *Middas HaDin*, people
ultimately get punished, so God doesn't just let things go. All right.
אלא מאריך רוחיה *Ela ma'arich ruchyei*, God might not punish right away.
He he, you know, he's ארך אפים *erech apayim*, he extends his
wrath, וגבי דידיה *vegabe di'dei*, in the end though, he'll collect what's
coming to him. So, what's the meaning? So, what's the answer here?
So, the answer is look, it looked like this guy was a
צדיק tzadik *tzaddik*, it looked like his child was a צדיק tzadik,
*tzaddik*. Don't worry. There's a right חשבון cheshbon *cheshbon* up in שמים
*Shamayim*, and even though you don't see how it's attributed, God there's
it's ultimately מידת הדין *Middas HaDin*. We have to assume that it's
just and that it's paying back for some sin in the past
that we're not aware of. So, basically just saying it's, you know,
we believe in God as a just God even if we don't
understand.
Oh, is
the
interim period, yes, but I think it's being used here, right. If
you see, that's a good point, if you see, meaning it's not
just if I'm going to sin and say God will forgive it.
But if you see somebody who's doing well, don't ask how is
he doing well? Did God just forgive his sin? Don't worry, God
will eventually collect what's due to him. Right, that's a good point,
that's a nice way of saying it because then you're not sort
of directly making the statement about here, you're just suggesting the sort
of reverse, you know, in this case. Yes.
There's another reason here, one of the commentators says that כי במידה
שאדם זהיר בה מאוד אם הוא פוגם קצת.
No,
no, no, no, we're getting to that. That's I don't see that
in this statement. That's going to come up. Don't worry, that point
is going to come up. Yes, but that's not I don't see
that being said here. That's going to come up in the next
in the next bit. So let's see. So that was one idea,
somehow, yes, the חשבון always works out. אמר רבי אחא כתיב, amar
rabbi acha kesiv, now Rabbi Acha
is going to say something else and which
it's a דרשה drasha on a פסוק pasuk but seems to be
answering how to how to relate to this phenomenon. The פסוק pasuk
says וסביביו נסערה מאוד, u-sevivav nis-ara me-od, around God it's very like
it's a whirlwind, that's the literal meaning. So מדקדק עמהם כחוט השערה.
medakdek imahem ke-chut ha-se-ara. So
סביביו, sevivav, those that are surround God, נסערה nis-ara from the word
שערה, se-ara, God is as exacting as like the hair breadth. So
the closer you are to God, the more he expects of you.
Right? And the bigger צדיק tzaddik you are, the more, you know,
then the higher standard you'll be held to. A, because you're you're
fit to be held to a higher standard. B, also presumably because
if you do something wrong it impacts on how people perceive God.
So the closer you are the higher standard you're held to, so
that's why we can't understand again how
he was punished, but as opposed to an idea of some old
sin that God was paying back for, it's no, God has an
extremely high standard and even if a guy was a total צדיק,
you know, he must have been held to a very, very high
standard.
It's like אהרן Aharon's sons.
It's like אהרן Aharon's sons, right, right, right. A common way of
רש"י Rashi explains the פסוק pasuk בקדושי, bi-kadoshai, בקרובי אקדש. bi-krovai ekadesh.
Exactly, right,
exactly. רש"י Rashi quotes this idea by the פסוק pasuk בקרובי אקדש.
bi-krovai ekadesh. אמר רבי יוסי לא מטעם הזה. amar rabbi yosi lo
mita-am hazeh. No, not based on that פסוק. pasuk. אלא ממה דכתיב,
ela mimah de-kesiv, what's meant by the verse, ונורא הוא על כל
סביביו, ve-nora hu al kol sevivav, God is awesome around all those
that surround him. מוראו על הקרובים יותר מן הרחוקים, mora-o al ha-krovim
yoser min ha-rechokim,
His awe is more on those that are close than those that
are far away. Now awe does not just mean I guess from
this sense how we experience God but also how God acts as
it were vis-à-vis us. So again it's that closeness and therefore that
or what's demanded in terms of that awe and therefore when somebody
oversteps, the consequences are so I don't understand if somebody here can
explain to me how that's conceptually different than what we said before
other than דרשנינג darshining from another פסוק. pasuk. I mean there is
a difference that one talks about God being exacting and the other
talks about the greater awe that a person has. So maybe it's
a difference between God demanding a higher standard and you understanding that,
you know, the that you should implicitly live up to a higher
standard because of because you know, because of that closeness. So it's
not as though God is imposing it. It's the awe in your
appreciation of God demands that higher standard. That's the best that I
can understand.
Maybe somebody can distinguish between these two different aspects of a person's
realities. One emphasizing the responsibilities for the behaviors that function. Right. The
other is complete interiority.
Yes, but if it's complete interiority then it's not relevant here. Why?
Because then
why does it do with why he was punished? Meaning if the
whole point it's making is the closer you are the more experience
you have of God, the more awe you need to have over
God, it doesn't explain it's not a response to why this happened.
So I think it means that because of that, that leads to
a greater demand, but more like a demand that almost emerges from
within rather than what emerges from without. That's what I was trying
to say.
Maybe they're more sensitive to the nuances of שכר ועונש. sachar va-onesh.
As if they understood the difference between these two phrasings. Right, just
trying to get a bit of a handle on it. Now what
דב Dov was saying before is what one of the מפרשים meforshim
tried to say, which is why was it דווקא davka that he
died in thirst was because somehow, and again I don't see this
clear in the text, but that somehow because he was the father
who was so invested, and this could be like the כחוט השערה
ke-chut ha-se-ara answer, so invested in the area of water, so therefore
in a way he was being held up to make sure that
he did absolutely the best in regards to that water. And therefore
if there was something that was even a little bit off, he
was going to get punished for it. So the מדקדק כחוט השערה
medakdek ke-chut ha-se-ara would be understood to be within the context of
his job of providing water in the בית המקדש. And that's why
his son died in thirst, so to explain actually, you know, that
almost מידה כנגד מידה midah k'neged midah in the in the ironic
way. So that's is, I think, building on the כחוט השערה. kichut
hasa'arah. רבי חגי, Rabbi Hagai, now let's look at the next story,
because the next story is
fascinating. רבי חגי בשם רבי שמואל בר נחמן: Rabbi Hagai b'shem Rabbi
Shmuel bar Nachman: מעשה בחסיד אחד, ma'aseh b'chasid echad, a story with
a חסיד chasid שהיה חופר בורות שיחין ומערות shehayah chofer boros shichin
u'm'aros לעוברים ושבים, l'ovrim v'shavim, not to the בית המקדש, he would
dig these wells for for the people that would, you know, go
by in their journey, you know, and obviously it was a time
when you couldn't just, you know, go ahead and go into a
store and get a Coke, so you know people would be obviously
very weary, and the more they had they had wells alongside, you
know, alongside the main road or or accessible, it was a tremendous,
tremendous טובה. tovah. So and he did this all presumably on his
own. פעם אחת pam achas היתה בתו עוברת להינשא, haysah bitto overes
l'hinasai, once his daughter was going to get married, so you know
to heighten the tragedy here, she was about to get married, ושטפה
נהר, u'shatafa nahar, and she got washed away by a river. So
again it's like a reverse מידה כנגד מידה. midah k'neged midah. He
was a צדיק in this area providing water, and she got punished
by water. הון כל עמא עלוי, havon kol amma alavei, everybody went
to visit him. עלין לגביה, a'alin lagabei, בעון מנחמתיה, ba'on m'nachamteh, and
they tried to give him consolation. ולא קיבל עליו, v'lo kibeil alav
he refused to accept, he refused to be consoled like יעקב אבינו,
Yaakov Avinu, right, who wouldn't be consoled, and by יעקב Yaakov he
wouldn't be consoled and it winds up that יוסף Yosef was alive.
So, and the רש"י Rashi there quotes the חז"ל Chazal that you
know that or it says that you know that that God was
גוזר gozer that the memory of the מת mes should like or
you know or the pain should be abated after twelve months, but
if the person is still alive, then somehow metaphysically it wasn't possible
for him to be consoled. Okay, so he refused to be consoled.
Now you could also read it as he was very angry that
דווקא davka the thing that he was, you know, it's almost like
an איוב Iyov story, right, the injustice, דווקא davka the thing that
he was so מחמיר machmir on, all of, now this happened to
his daughter on her wedding day. So he refused to be consoled.
על רבי פנחס בן יאיר, al Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair, ah, רבי
פנחס בן יאיר Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair
makes another visit. He came לגביה lagabei to him, בעי מנחמתיה, ba'ei
m'nachamteh, he wanted to console him,
ולא קיבל v'lo kibeil עליו alav, מנחמתא, m'nachamta, he refused to accept
the
consolation. אמר להון, amar l'hon,
so he said to them like the people around, you know, the
people in the neighborhood, the friends, דין הוא חסידכון? dein hu chasid'chum?
This is your חסיד? chasid? That he you know he refuses to
be consoled? Refuses to be consoled means you don't accept God's justice?
That you think that you know that like you have a טענה
taina against God? So אמרו ליה, amru leh, they said to him,
רבי, כך וכך היה עושה, kach v'kach hayah oseh, look, let me
explain to you what the story is. It's not just סתם stam
a guy who lost his daughter. This is what he would do,
he would dig these wells, כך וכך אירע לה, kach v'kach eira
lah, this is how his daughter died. It's you know it's incomprehensible
to him. אמר, so he said, אפשר שהיה מכבד את בוראו במים,
efshar shehayah mekhabed es boro b'mayim, is it possible that he honored
his creator with water והוא מקפח במים, v'hu mekapei'ach b'mayim, and God
is going to now cut him off like you know injure him
with water? מיד נפלה הברה בעיר, miyad naflah havarah ba'ir, immediately a
like a commotion arose in the city. באת בתו של אותו איש,
ba'as bitto shel oso ish, and the daughter came back alive. Okay,
you know, showed up alive. אית דאמרי, is d'amri, now how did
she survive? Some say בסוכתא איסתבכית, b'suchsa istabchis, that she grabbed onto
a branch as she was being washed away by the river. ואית
דאמרי, v'is d'amri, some say מלאך ירד כדמות רבי פנחס בן יאיר
והצילה. malach yarad kidmus Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair v'hitzilah. An angel came
down looking like רבי פנחס בן יאיר Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair's face.
So that was רבי פנחס בן יאיר's Rabbi Pinchas ben Yair's statement
that ultimately of course what this means is I think the point
here is if he hadn't said it she would have died. But
in a way because he couldn't accept that, right, and you know
he sort of said this is inappropriate, so somehow some miracle happened,
some deus ex machina happened and she actually wound up that she
had survived. And that's I think the message of the מלאך malach
of פנחס בן יאיר, Pinchas ben Yair, it was his intervention that
made her survive. Now maybe it's just two ways to read the
story. The other way and maybe this is if it wasn't his
intervention and just happened naturally, it's that in the end it's sort
of saying yeah God would never do it. פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas
ben Yair didn't do anything special. If something this unjust God would
never let happen, and actually it turned out that it was a
misunderstanding and lo and behold she hadn't died. If you read and
so in a way it's interesting when you juxtapose this story to
what preceded, right? Because what's the justice of the previous story? And
here we have a story. So one way of reading the story
is you know what? Forget about that. Whatever the answer is that's
the answer. The general rule is God would never do such a
thing like this, right? And therefore we have to assume that you
know that
that hopefully there'll always be another explanation, interpretation, why God would never
actually punish somebody in exactly that thing that they were you know
so wonderful in. But the other possible reading is no, actually, like
the previous story, sometimes it does happen, and it's only the intervention
of פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair that allowed that to sort
of not happen in that case. Okay, it's also interesting to think
about what is the difference between what רבי פנחס בן יאיר Rabbi
Pinchas ben Yair said and this guy's refusal to accept consolation. It's
basically was the same point, right? But... But the difference might have
been that it's like, how could it, you know, how could God
do this, right? I was so great in this, and now I'm
being punished this way. But it could be the point is is
that פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair refused to believe that it
was true. Right? They both accepted that it would make no sense,
but if you believe that it's true, then you have a טענה
taina against God. He refused to believe it was true, there must
be another explanation. And in a way I think that goes back
to the previous story. You know, we have to like believe, the
attitude here is you have to believe in God's justice. You have
to- you refuse to believe it's true that this should be unjust.
We might not know the answer, but rather than saying it's unjust
and having a טענה taina against God, רב פנחס בן יאיר'ס Reb
Pinchas ben Yair's response is no, you can't accept that it's unjust,
there's some explanation. Okay, so I think it's a very nice closure
to that previous story.
The consolation, it wasn't that the father refused to believe that the
daughter died, it was that he believed the daughter-
and he had a טענה taina against God.
Right, right, and he refused to believe-
and he didn't want to be consoled cause he was angry.
And in some ways- and some says it could make sense.
Right, right, it's like an איוב Iyov story in a way, right?
This reminds me of the אלישע Elisha story of reviving the dead,
the child. Oh, right, because he intervened. Right, he intervened, right, exactly.
It's almost like everyone else, exactly, exactly.
But this kind of stepping in and opposing what appears to be
the divine imperative, the divine action
is the- what stands out here.
Exactly, exactly. The whole idea of an angel that looked like רב
פנחס בן יאיר, Reb Pinchas ben Yair, you know, some say oh
you're such an angel, so here he was, he was the angel,
the angel that looked like רב פנחס בן יאיר. Reb Pinchas ben
Yair. Okay, גביני כרוז, Gvini Kruz, let's try to get a little
bit more. Now גביני Gvini was the announcer שהיה מכריז בבית המקדש.
she'aya machriz b'Beis HaMikdash. He would make the announcements in the בית
המקדש. מה היה אומר, Ma haya omer, what would he say? עמדו
הכהנים לעבודה, Imdu Hakohanim l'avoda,
he would get every- he would wake everybody up, maybe if they
were sleeping, or he would get everybody into their posts when the
time came. Oh הכהנים, get to the עבודה, avoda, לוים לדוכנם, Leviim
l'duchanam, לוים Leviim
get to your stations, you know, where they're going to do the
שירה. shira. ישראל למעמדם, Yisrael l'maamadam, and Jews go to the מעמד
maamad which is the sort of representation of the Jewish people that
stood by the קרבן תמיד. korban tamid. אגריפס המלך שמע קולו עד
ח' פרסאות. Agrippas HaMelech shama kolo ad cheis parsa'os. So
אגריפס Agrippas heard the- his voice, he had a very thundering voice,
eight par- eight פרסאות parsa'os away, which is like eight kilometers. One
assumes it's a bit of an exaggeration. ונתנו לו מתנות הרבה, V'nasnu
lo matanos harbeh, and he gave him a lot of gifts. I
don't know why, cause he thought, oh you're doing such a good
job, let me encourage you. Okay, בן גבר על נעילת שערים. Ben
Gever al ne'ilas she'arim. בן גבר Ben Gever oversaw the closing of
the gates, locking the gates, which is the- the job of the
לוים. Leviim. So
תירגס- Tirgas תרגם, Tirgeim, excuse me, רב קומי דבי רב שילה, Rav
Kumi d'bei Rav Shila, קרא גברא. Kra Gavra. Now the- the- there's
a-
there's a משנה Mishna that said that they would do the תרומת
המזבח, trumas hamizbeach, not the תרומת הלשכה, trumas halishka, but the תרומת
הדשן trumas hadeshen when it was- when the- when the- when there
was- when at the- when- I'm just
trying to get the exact phrase here... the phrase is, hold on...
קריאת
הגבר.
krias hagever.
So at the קריאת הגבר krias hagever they would do the תרומת
הלשכה. trumas halishka. So what's קריאת הגבר? krias hagever? So the way
it's normally explained is גבר Gever is a word for a rooster,
and it was when the rooster crows. Okay, so he translated it
as-
as קרא גברא. Kra Gavra. קרא גברא אכריז כרוזא. Kra Gavra achriz
kruza. So he translated this קרא גבר, Kra Gever, קריאת הגבר, krias
hagever, as the announcer made his announcements. Meaning he connected it, first
of all, to the fact that it says בן גבר, Ben Gever,
okay, and he was the one- oh no, he was the נעילת
שערים, ne'ilas she'arim, excuse me. So anyway, so he but said it
means that the announcer made the announcement. גבר Gever literally means גבר,
Gever, it doesn't mean a rooster. Okay, אמר ליה, Amar lei, אימא
קרא תרנגולא, eimur kra tarnagola, why don't you say it means when
the rooster crows? אמר ליה, Amar lei, והתנינן בן גבר, v'ha t'ninan
Ben Gever, because our משנה Mishna talks about a בן גבר, Ben
Gever, it was a guy's name. איסלקא למימר בר תרנגולא, Isalach lemeimar
bar tarnagola, the son of a rooster? Which is such a funny
answer, but he's basically saying is I'd rather not explain that the
word גבר Gever means- means a rooster. I'd rather assume that it
means a man. Okay, so clearly that's what it means here and
anyway that's what he would read it there as not the rooster
but the- you know, not the rooster but about the announcer. Okay,
let's look a little bit more. בן בבי על הפקיע. Ben Babi
al hapaki'a. בן בבי Ben Babi oversaw the פקיע. paki'a. So what's
the פקיע? paki'a? שהיה מזייד פתילות. shehaya m'zayed ptilos. That he would
basically twist the threads that would be used, you know, the- the
פתילות ptilos that would be used in the מנורה. Menorah. רבי יוסי
על כופרא. Reb Yosi al kuphra. So רבי יוסי Reb Yosi came
to כופרא. kuphra. בעא ממיניה עליהון פרנסין. Ba m'manya ilayon parnasin. He
wanted to appoint people to be פרנסין, parnasin, which is people to-
administer צדקה, tzedaka, so it's a lot of responsibility. But he wanted
to make people, he wanted to do something about how they were
handling the צדקה tzedaka in the city and wanted to appoint פרנסין.
parnasin. ולא קיבלו מנהון. V'lo kiblu mineihon. They refuse- they didn't want
to accept, they didn't want to take the job. אזל ואמר קמיהון.
Azal v'amar kameihon. He got up, interesting phrase, meaning like it was
a דרשה, drasha, maybe on שבת, Shabbos, and he said
to
them... not a very big, big deal in the thing in the
בית המקדש. It had to get done, wasn't such a big deal
though, okay compared to the other stuff. So זכה להימנות עם גדולי
הדור, zachah limanos im gedolei hador, and he was mentioned with the
great ones in the משנה, mishna, the people that obviously had much
more jobs of much greater significance. אתם שאתם נמנים על חיי נפשות,
atem sheatem nimnaim al chayei nefashos, you, if you take, you or
you'll be appointed on an issue that's of life and death, making
sure that the poor get the food that they need, וכל שכן,
vechol sheken, how much more so will you be counted amongst the
great ones. So yes, taking positions of authority and of responsibility is
a lot of work, but look at this, look at the type
of, you know, כבוד kavod and the that is deserving and the
importance of that. Okay, then ארזא על הצלצל, Arza al hatzaltzal, just
a little bit more, he would be over the like the the
you know the the clanging of the like of the of the
chimes or the triangle. הכי דתנינא תמן, hachi detanina taman, הניף הסגן
בסודרין henif hasgan besudarim when they were bringing the תמיד, tamid, you
had to do the singing at the moment the קרבן korban was
being brought. So the, so the assistant would wave with the flags
because it's a good way to communicate at a distance. והקיש בן
ארזא על הצלצל, veheikish ben Arza al hatzaltzal, he banged the chimes
or banged like a triangle or a gong or whatever it was,
more like a chime. And then the לויים Leviim began the singing
and the playing of the instrument. והוגרס בן לוי על השיר, veHugras
ben Levi al hashir, הוגרס בן לוי, Hugras ben Levi,
now here he was from the לוי Levi family, so he oversaw
the שיר, shir, the actual singing of the לויים. Leviim. אמר אבא
נעימה יתירה היה יודע, amar ava neima yeseira haya yodeia, he knew
a very beautiful melody. ואמרו עליו על הוגרס בן לוי שהיה מנעימה
את קולו בזמר, ve'amru alav al Hugras ben Levi shehaya mane'ima es
kolo bezemer, he would be able to you know make his voice
extremely melodious with melody or accompany, you know, accompany with music. וכשהיה
נועץ גודלו בתוך פיו, ukshehaya no'es gudalo besoch piv, and
he would stick his thumb in his mouth, היה מוציא כמה מיני
זמר, haya motzi kama minei zemer, he would be able to make
many different types of amazing sounds you know by sticking his thumb
in his mouth, I don't know, it's like anyway like whistling or
something, I don't know, והיו כל הכהנים נזרקים לו בבת ראש, vehayu
kol hakohanim nizrakim lo bevash rosh, and all the כהנים would be
like exactly what this phrase means like something but somehow it means
like they would be, you know like
startled, taken aback at how amazing and how powerful this music was.
Okay so I guess we'll end here, the whole story about the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim and these houses that wouldn't teach it, we'll
have to wait for tomorrow. All right.